[clears throat]
>> Ajahn,
I want to let go of my opinions
because I see how arguing about who is
right causes me problems
causes me problems
and stress.
But I often just end up adopting a new
so-called better view to place the old
one which just creates a new source of
which just creates a new source of
friction with others.
Political, religious,
weather, diet, uh uh exercises, whatever
it is.
Can I actually hold a view without
having it cause internal tension
due to being in con- conflict with
opposing views?
Uh
and if not, how can I not hold to any
view at all? Is that even possible?
>> Well, I think the the whole
the whole question is based on the
premise that the view is the problem.
But it isn't. The problem is that they
can't uh not
uh not
They cannot argue. They can't restrain
their speech. That's the problem.
Because yes, you it's impossible to just
choose to not hold any views cuz you'll
be holding that view.
Uh but what you described, what the
question describes, means like the views
are not the issue. The issue is that
that person can't help themselves but
argue about the views.
But if you restrain your speech and
don't argue about your views, then
what's the conflict?
There is no conflict.
>> if you like you're attached to your view
of
>> Well, you are attached to your views.
View means the existential standpoint.
So it's not like oh, I can impartially
hold a view.
Like you are you you are invested in it.
Like sometimes more, sometimes less, but
view is not a holding a view is not a
neutral thing.
Uh so
you could say oh, holding a view is the
root of suffering. Well, you could also
say non-restraint is the root of
suffering. Because again, you can hold the views,
Because again, you can hold the views,
other people can hold their views, but
there will be no conflict for as long as
you don't act out of your views.
Either through argument or trying to
change other people's behavior and so
on. So, you want to avoid the conflict,
So, you want to avoid the conflict,
avoid the disruption, restrain your
speech. Don't talk about your views.
Don't talk about your views.
>> So, can you have Can you have a view
then about whatever it is, say a
political view,
you think is right and then you you hear
an opposing view?
>> Yeah.
>> And and not get
>> Yeah, so that's unpleasant, but that's
still not the source of
conflict. The conflict begins when you
start acting out.
There's always going to be things that
are displeasing to you in the world. So,
you're either going to take that for
granted and then try and change the
world, or you're going to recognize that, okay,
or you're going to recognize that, okay,
I have to draw lines somewhere for my
mind and then not not act out to the
extent they would be actually causing
conflict and adding
further passion and discomfort and suffering on
passion and discomfort and suffering on
account of already existing, say,
discrepancies between what I believe and
what others believe.
So, then after, like say, when you're
not adding more fuel to those things,
you could
um
pretty much, like through the same type
of training that we often describe,
um
reduce even the mental involvement, so
to speak. Like the mental proliferation,
mental choices,
uh um they would be adding,
say, to the views and to the to the
weight of those views. So, then even if
you hear the opposing views,
like you will not be um affected
emotionally as much as before. Because
again, you learn how not to be invested
in your views emotionally.
But that development of non-investment
in your views emotionally can only begin
if you stop acting out of the investment
in your views emotionally, which is
speaking out of your views, arguing with
your views, defending your views,
um you know, proving others wrong and
all of that. Like that has to be subdued
first so that you can get to the source
of the problem.
But the way the question was formulated
implies that oh yeah,
there is conflict, there is suffering
when I meet the opposed views and then
everything that arises from it and you
know, you argue and you this and the
disagreements. Oh, if only I could not
have views then everything would be
fine. It's like true. Everything would
be fine when you go beyond views, i.e.
when you're an arahant. But in order to
get that, you have to stop making it
worse through speaking out of your views, or
through speaking out of your views, or
doing this out of your views, or doing
that out of your views.
>> [snorts]
>> There's that There's that one attempt or
one view that
tries to get free from all views and
free from the suffering that comes
that's around holding views.
The attempt of well,
I don't hold to any views and
everything's every view is just okay,
whatever. I just go with whatever.
>> Yeah, it's the
>> It's like that is a view in itself.
>> as I said, a desperate attempt
to find a way out.
>> Or I I don't say I don't agree with or I
don't disagree with your view.
>> Yeah, trying to trying to maintain
neutrality >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> as a view,
which can only go so far.
Because that is your view that you
depend on. So if somebody challenges
that neutrality,
>> Yeah.
>> which it will be challenged sooner or
later, you'll see that you still very
much hold the views.
And then you just try to as I said,
retroactively convince yourself that
convince yourself that
I don't hold to any views. What I'm
practicing non-holding to any views.
It's like
>> But it comes out of opposition to.
>> Yeah, of course. Of course, comes as a
response to the to the actual
uh discomfort that there is on account
of your views that you hold.
>> [snorts]
>> So, it's you can't just as I said paste
the wishful thinking
on your mind and say don't hold to any
views cuz that very much is going to be
something that you hold.
And if you if you still believe it
isn't, well,
if they were true, then you would be
going throughout your day days not
upset, not uh not moved by sensual
desire, not moved by irritation.
All of those are symptoms of holding
existential positions that are
contradictory, that are wrong, that are
discrepant, that are based on greed,
aversion, distraction, and so on.
So, people cuz as I said, people can say
that they don't hold to any fixed views,
but what does your practice and life
around tell you? Like is the mind coming
up with stuff? Are you acting out of it
means you very much hold to a view.
>> And preferences like
>> Of course. Of course.
>> I want the dishes to be washed in a
certain way at a certain time with a
certain method, and then someone doesn't
do that.
>> Well, yeah.
Yeah. Cuz all of those are views, by the
way. >> Yeah, exactly.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Like
you know, suttas when they when they
when they were sort of boiled down to
these these like extremely generic stock
passages that we have today lost all the
nuances. So, when we read those parts
when it says, "Oh, here is someone in
Brahman goes and kind of withdraws
himself physically from centrality,
but then they start holding views."
That's the usual translation. They start
arguing about is the world eternal? Is
the world not eternal? And so on. And
people think it's like some sort of
optional uh abstract metaphysical debate that
uh abstract metaphysical debate that
monks will start having suddenly when
they live withdrawn from desire. It's
like, "No, no, no. That was just a
generic phrase
to refer to the utmost kind of
uh uh end points of all sorts of views
that you can have cuz all the views will
boil down to you either believe you're
going to live forever or you believe
everything is material and there is no
afterlife and so on. But practically
pretty much any preference, any
standpoint would fall within the scope
of eternalism and annihilationism in the
in the sutras. So even people they don't
think about whether their self is real
or whether we live after death or not
they fall into these categories. That's
what the Brahmins Chala Sutta describes.
These are like the netto views that come
from the source of like it's either this
or this and from there you get two, from
two you get four, eight, 16 and so on.
So
when when people read that Sutta about
holding the views, that's what it means.
Means when you live withdrawn from
sensuality and we seen that in the
monasteries. When you live withdrawn
from sensuality, everything else becomes
very important. How did you put that
broom? >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> Did you Did you turn around the the you
know Did you Did you change the the the
knob on the this end cuz I told you not
to. I told you to put the latch this way
and it becomes like immediate kind of
like like like mental sort of a visceral
reaction to all these little
preferences. And then people believe oh but I don't
And then people believe oh but I don't
hold to any views but here I am annoyed
by every little thing or provoked by
every little thing that's not to my
liking. So well that's already those are the
So well that's already those are the
views and those are the views because of
which then Samanas and Brahmins start to
fall out and argue.
Oh well we that's not how we wrapped the
rope here. Well those sandals are
technically too long of the laces and
you must have this and look at the whole
commentaries in the Vinaya and the
subsequent kind of arguments that were
kind of canonized.
>> Yeah.
>> Of just like absolute complete loss of
perspective proliferation.
You know like the
>> Acting out of views that's all born.
>> It's all It's all exactly It all comes
acting out of views cuz now that becomes
your main preoccupation. And the And the
training is the same. You stopped acting
out of course sensuality. Well now stop
acting out of these things, but now it's
becoming a bit more personal.
You know, like
Okay, you know, uh I keep the precepts.
I live in the monastery and so on, but
then you have yeah, these views that nag
you the whole day.
Oh, you know, I told him six times to
put the shoes in the rack.
And he still did doesn't put them in the
rack. >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> That's obviously your view, your
standpoint. What should be done?
You acted out cuz obviously you perceive
some sort of authority because you're
more senior or something.
It didn't happen.
Oh, now [snorts] it's adding more to it.
Now it's like well, well, is he
disrespecting me now? Is he doing that
out of disrespect? Or you
And then the mind gets even more
involved. And then what do you do?
Do you do the same as before? Okay, I'm
wanting cuz this is now the course
level. So, I'll stop fueling it first to
get to the bottom of it. Or do I take it
for granted and justify it? Because no,
I have to do it cuz if he doesn't do it,
everybody else will do it and then the
monastery will look like crap and then
we got to fix it and we got to
It's like views. And you fell into a
trap of it.
>> So, there you you see that you're
holding that view. You see you being you
you're triggering you.
>> Well, that's exactly So, how do I know
if I hold the view? Well, is there a an
emotional response
>> Yeah.
>> to the to the opposing view? To the
opposing idea, to the opposing
preference. If there is an emotional
response, means you are holding it.
>> And what do you need to do is not act
out >> Well, not add more to it.
>> by speech
>> That's how you begin by speech, through
action, don't take it for granted. When
then the mind is subdued on that
like as I said, more refined from the
course sensuality level,
then it's like as I said, the space
opens up. Then it's like, okay, I do
have a preference. There is a challenge
to a preference, but I can actually
maintain the perspective in regard to
both. And it doesn't matter if that challenge
And it doesn't matter if that challenge
remains for 1 day, 2 days, 3 days, 6
months. Perspective is unchanged.
Container remains there holding it both.
And then you realize, "Oh, actually, I'm
not I do have a preference, but I'm not
holding to view that's implicit in it."
But you can't just start with that
while you're still undermining it
through your actions and your speech and
so on. And and justifying doing so.